Guide to the Abraham Joshua Heschel Papers, 1880, 1919-1998 and undated RL.10086
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1880, 1921-1990s and undated; 6; 245 Boxes
  - Notes, 1880, circa 1930s-1970s and undated; 10
    - Various lecture notes, undated (Box 268, Folder 9)
      Contains handwritten notes on a variety of topics related to Judaism, particularly about prophecy and the Spirit of holiness.
    - Violence, undated (Box 268, Folder 10)
      Mix of handwritten and typed notes on a variety of topics including violence, polarity, and living.
    - Youth: [Miscellaneous writings], undated (Box 268, Folder 11)
      Mix of handwritten notes and annotated/fragments of typescripts clipped together in broad themes including Aging, Celebration, and Embarrassment.
    - זלאזיץ, undated (Box 268, Folder 12)
      Transliteration: Zalozits
      Translation: Zalozce
      Contains handwritten notes about the book Netiah shel simchah.
    - Books, 1921, 1950s-1960s (Box 269, Folder 1)
      A mix of handwritten notes, typescripts and clippings related to the Hasidic rabbis. Includes a receipt belonging to Joseph Miller for one shekel issued by the Executive Zionist Organization of London on June 19, 1921.
    - אשכול, 1956-1957 (Box 269, Folder 2)
      Contains a mixture of handwritten and typescript materials about a variety of topics, most notably the individual, precepts, and man.
    - Observance: Finkelstein, circa 1960s (Box 269, Folder 3)
      Primarily handwritten notes related to a variety of topics including Christianity, dogma, and faith.
    - Printed, circa 1960s (Box 269, Folder 4)
      Mix of typescripts, handwritten notes, and clippings on a variety of topics including Kierkegaard, The Baal Shem Tov, and marriage.
    - שונות, 1972 (Box 269, Folder 5)
      Mix of handwritten notes, typescripts, and clippings on a variety of topics including monasticism and theology.
    - Different Zaddikim, undated (Box 269, Folder 6)
      Contains handwritten tales about zaddikim. Also contains two handwritten citations.
    - אשכול [Eshkol]: Eshkol Conference, undated (Box 269, Folder 7)
      Handwritten notes primarily on the topic of Judaism and Jewish education.
    - אשכול [Eshkol]: [Writings and notes on religious topics], undated (Box 269, Folder 8)
      Contains a mixture of handwritten and typescript materials about a variety of religious topics.
    - R. Baruch, undated (Box 269, Folder 9)
      Contains handwritten Hasidic tales.
    - To be typed, undated (Box 269, Folder 10)
      Two handwritten pages of quotation, expounding passages from bible (Numbers 15 and Proverbs 8).
    - [Rabbi Ishmael and Rabbi Akiva], 1965 (Box 269, Folder 11)
      Contains two pages of handwritten quotations from Bavli Sanhedrin by Heschel; copy of two papers (term papers?) on Rabbis Ishmael and Akiva written for Heschel.
    - [Arab-Jewish relations], circa 1960s (Box 269, Folder 12)
      Primarily typed quotations related to Arab-Jewish relations.
    - List of Hasidic Mss., undated (Box 269, Folder 13)
      Contains handwritten lists of Hasidic manuscripts at Hebrew Union College (HUC).
    - [כתבי יד קורץ] - MSS Koretz, undated (Box 269, Folder 14)
      Transliteration: Kitve yad Koretz
      Translation: Koretz manuscripts
      Contains handwritten lists of numbered entries, possibly describing the contents of manuscripts.
    - מסודר, undated (Box 269, Folder 15)
      Translation: Organized
      Includes handwritten notes, on topics including the Tablets of the Covenant, the generations of Adam, principles of divine governance and existence, edited off-print of Heschel's chapter in Finkelstein's The Jews.
    - שיריים, undated (Box 270, Folder 1)
      Transliteration: Shirim
      Translation: Poems/Songs/Religious Exposition
      Primarily consists of lists of books which are organized alphabetically.
    - בעש"ט 41 קאזלאוו, undated (Box 270, Folder 2)
      Transliteration: Beshṭ 41 Kozolov
      Translation: Baal Shem Tov 41 Kozolov
      A mix of photocopies, handwritten notes, typescripts and bibliographic citations related to the Baal Shem Tov.
    - שונות, undated (Box 270, Folder 3)
      Primarily typescripts on a variety of theological topics.
  - Other Writings by Heschel, circa 1930s-1993 and undated; 11
    This subseries includes materials which could be identified as related to Heschel's writings. The types of writings includes tributes, typescripts (in a variety of working draft states) of articles and essays some of which were ultimately published and some presumably unpublished, newspaper articles, editorials, book reviews, galley proofs, and typescripts of interviews with Heschel. Also included are a small amount of handwritten notes, lists and correspondence that are specific to Heschel's writings and materials which are not related to Heschel's writings but were included in the folder. Note that not all typescripts include a title or author name, but were identified as Heschel's based largely on his handwritten corrections or annotations on the typescripts. The materials are arranged chronologically.
    - Belege, 1935-1937; 1 of 2 (Box 271, Folder 1)
      Mix of materials including form letters from Erich Reiss Verlag to various editors promoting Die Prophetie, calendars from 1936 and 1937, and a 2 page galley proof from Heschel's Das Prophetische Bewusstsein. Also contains a large amount of clippings written by Heschel including editorials, book reviews, and memoriam.
    - Belege, 1935-1937; 2 of 2 (Box 271, Folder 2)
    - Gebet, circa 1936; 1 of 2 (Box 271, Folder 3)
      Contains handwritten lists of a wide variety of names and addresses of individuals and professional periodicals presumably to whom copies of this publication were to be sent for review or commentary.
    - Gebet, circa 1936; 2 of 2 (Box 271, Folder 4)
    - [Miscellaneous writing], 1938 (Box 271, Folder 5)
      Several versions of a typescript written by Heschel entitled "Versuch einer Deutung."
    - [Portfolio], 1938-1945 (Box 271, Folder 6)
      Mix of materials related to Heschel's early years at Hebrew Union College and to a smaller degree his time in London. Includes HUC Bulletins, course descriptions, and two typescripts by Heschel: "Prayer and the Spiritual Life" and "On the Essence of Hebrew Prayer" (from Bitzaron Hebrew Monthly). Also includes pamphlets on lectures offered at the Institute for Jewish Learning in London which were mailed to Heschel and a bulletin from the Theodor Herzl Society.
    - [Das Gerücht - Eine Rede], 1938-1940 (Box 271, Folder 7)
      Transliteration: The Rumor - A Discourse
      Materials related to "Das Gerücht - Eine Rede" which Heschel wrote for Hamizrachi Chajenu. Also contains several bulletins (Mitteilungsblatt) for the Theodor Herzl Society and a form letter announcing the opening of the Institute for Jewish Learning in London.
    - Gebet, 1939 (Box 271, Folder 8)
      Contains a corrected typescript "Das Gebet als Äusserung und Einfühlung" and a copy of the offprint which includes handwritten notes.
    - [Prayer as Expression and Empathy], 1939 and undated (Box 271, Folder 9)
      Contains two corrected typescripts of Prayer as Expression and Empathy translated by Maurice Friedman. Also includes original offprint publication Das Gebet als Äusserung und Einfühlung.
    - Auth, circa 1930s (Box 272, Folder 1)
      Language(s): All materials in German with the exception of the annotations which are in Hebrew.
      Contains annotated typescript "Abraham Heschel - Materialien für eine Ausdrucken und Problemgeschichte fes Anthropomorphismus", with another draft with the title page: "Ihrem Lehrer Hernn Prof. Ismar Elbogen in Dankbarkeit und lieben der Verehrung Ueberichtet von Fritz Aronstein, Peter Freund, Abraham Heschel, Gustav Ormann und Heinz Wolff." Appears to be unpublished.
    - Gebet Bibliographie, circa 1940 (Box 272, Folder 2)
      Handwritten bibliography primarily on the topic of prayer but also includes the Bible and philosophy. Also contains handwritten manuscript "Die Schwierigkeit" which is labeled as "used."
    - Piety, 1941 (Box 272, Folder 3)
      Includes corrected typescript titled "Analysis of Piety" and a handwritten draft of Hebrew essay on the theme of Yir'at Shamayim (Fear of Heaven).
    - Piety, 1941 (Box 272, Folder 4)
      Extensively revised handwritten draft of "Analysis of Piety".
    - יראת שמים, 1942 (Box 272, Folder 5)
      Translation: God-fearing
      Contains handwritten notes of an article by Heschel about God-fearing, accompanied by a letter from the Hebrew weekly ha-Doʼar, to which it had been submitted.
    - Holocaust, 1942-1944 (Box 272, Folder 6)
      4-page typescript likely related Heschel's article "The Meaning of This War." Also includes a clipping advertising a "Soul Saving Revival" conducted by Rev. C. L. Lindsey at the Metropolitan Baptist Church.
    - Saadia, circa 1942-1944 (Box 272, Folder 7)
      All handwritten notes, most likely working drafts for Heschel's article"The Quest for Certainty in Saadia's Philosophy."
    - [Miscellaneous], 1943-1972; 1 of 2 (Box 272, Folder 8)
      Mix of materials related to a variety of topics. Materials include typed addresses by Julian Morgenstern, typed address "Man is Not Alone" given by Heschel at the University of Connecticut, reports on religion and freedom and intermarriage, and a small amount of correspondence related to Heschel's speeches and lectures. Also includes the newspaper article "No Faith Without Effort" written by Heschel for The Jewish Chronicle.
    - [Miscellaneous], 1943-1972; 2 of 2 (Box 273, Folder 1)
    - Ashkenazim and Sephardic, 1944 and undated (Box 273, Folder 2)
      Primarily corrected typescripts and proof pages and a printed and clean offprint of Heschel's article "Faith" (reprinted from The Reconstructionist and published by The Jewish Reconstruction Foundation). Also contains untitled lightly corrected typescript.
    - פקוח נשמה, circa 1949 (Box 273, Folder 3)
      Translation: [Saving a soul]
      Handwritten notes, presumably related to Heschel's article "[To Save a Soul]."
    - פקוח נשמה, circa 1949 (Box 273, Folder 4)
    - Last Days of Maimonides, circa 1949, 1955 (Box 273, Folder 5)
      Mix of annotated typescripts and handwritten notes related to Maimonides. Also includes two articles Heschel wrote about Maimonides; The National Jewish Monthly contains "The Last Years of Maimonides". The other article is from the Yiddish newspaper, "The Day" (דער טאג), June 2, 1949.
    - From Mysticism, circa 1940s (Box 273, Folder 6)
      Mix of handwritten notes and typescripts which appear to be related to article Heschel wrote on Jewish Mysticism. Also contains galley proof for Heschel's article "The Mystical Elements in Judaism."
    - Hebrew, 1952-1958 (Box 273, Folder 7)
      A mix of typescripts and correspondence including correspondence with leaders at The Jewish Agency, the School of Education at Hebrew University and Israel's Ministry of Education and Culture. Includes typescripts by Heschel on Jewish education and Shabbat.
    - [מקורות לתורה התפלה], 1953 (Box 273, Folder 8)
      Transliteration: Meḳorot le-Torah ha-Tefilah
      Translation: Sources on the Teaching of Prayer
      Typescript for an article entitled "Mekorot le'Torah ha'Tefilla."
    - [Galley proofs - Rabbinical Assembly Yearbook], 1953 (Oversize-box 8, Folder 7)
      Includes two corrected galley proofs; Heschel's "The Spirit of Jewish Prayer" and the discussion that followed Heschel and Rabbi Eugene Kohn's papers.
    - [Galley proof - The Spirit of Jewish Education], 1953 (Oversize-box 8, Folder 8)
      Galley proof of Heschel's article from Comet: Jewish Education.
    - Eulogies, 1953, 1960-1961 (Box 273, Folder 9)
      Contains draft and final typescript eulogies for Ilya Shor, Hillel Bavli, and Luba Dinkin. Also includes correspondence and typescript related to a request for Heschel to review Milton Steinberg's article "Anatomy of Faith."
    - [Galley Proofs], circa 1953-1954; 1 of 2 (Box 274, Folder 1)
      Various corrected galley proofs from the Rabbinical Assembly Yearbook which includes Heschel's "Toward an Understanding of the Halacha" and "The Spirit of Jewish Prayer." Also includes a corrected galley proof of the opening discussion at the Central Conference of American Rabbis and a galley proof of Heschel's article "Das Wesen der Dinge nach der Lehre Gabirols."
    - [Galley Proofs], circa 1953-1954; 2 of 2 (Box 274, Folder 2)
    - Prayer: Prayer, 1953-1954 (Box 274, Folder 3)
      Mix of handwritten notes, drafts, annotated typescripts and fragments related to prayer, and correspondence from Charles Scribner's Sons related to publication of Man's Quest for God and a reader's honorarium in connection with Heschel's reading of a manuscript. Also includes a letter from Steven Schwarzchild responding to a CCAR paper Heschel had sent to him, and a Hebrew manuscript written by Heschel about sources of Torah and prayer presumably written at the Jewish Theological Seminary.
    - Unknown R, 1953-1954 (Box 274, Folder 4)
      Contains annotated typescript "The Situation of the Jewish Man" which discusses Jewish faith, heritage and piety. Presumably written by Heschel.
    - [The Spirit of Hebrew Prayer], 1954 (Oversize-box 8, Folder 9)
      Proofs for "The Spirit of Hebrew Prayer", Hebrew translation in Megillot
    - [Galley proof - A Hebrew Evaluation of Reinhold Niebuhr], 1956 (Oversize-box 8, Folder 10)
      Unmarked galley proof of Heschel's contribution to Reinhold Niebuhr: His Religious, Social, and Political Thought.
    - Free Society, 1958 (Box 274, Folder 5)
      Annotated proof sheets with inserted typescript pages of "The Religious Message."
    - [Miscellaneous manuscripts], 1958 (Box 274, Folder 6)
      Includes corrected typescript, "The Nature of Faith" by Abraham Heschel, a handwritten manuscript "The Hasidic Concept of בין אדם לחבורו [Bein Adam Le'Chavero]. Also includes handwritten notes in German on the topic of Dimension.
    - Bea NY, 1958-1961 (Box 274, Folder 7)
      Mix of materials including Heschel's typed address from the National Women's League of the United Synagogue of America convention, a review of a book by Will Herberg, correspondence related to some of Heschel's books, and clippings related to Heschel's talk in Argentinia and an article by Heschel in דרום entitled היחיד הדורנו
    - [Miscellaneous], 1959 (Box 274, Folder 8)
      A poem, "Is Now," by Mark Van Doren and an article from The Zionist Quarterly, "To Be A Jew: What Is It?" by Heschel.
    - AJH Essays, 1959-1961, 1970, 1972 (Box 274, Folder 9)
      A mix of handwritten notes and typescripts. Contains conference material for "An Ecumenical Witness" Conference which includes "The Reason for My Involvement in the Peace Movement" by Heschel. Includes galley proofs of an article Heschel wrote for ha-Doʼar, בעיית היהדות בדורנו, [The Problem of Judaism in our Generation] and a handwritten list of publications. Also contains the Spring 1972 issue of the United Synagogue Review which includes a number of letters to the editor regarding an article Heschel wrote in a previous issue.
    - Weinfeld, circa 1950s (Box 274, Folder 10)
      Contains outline by Heschel for possible article on theology at the end of the First Temple; an article titled 'Between Science and Faith;" and other notes.
    - [Miscellaneous], 1960 and undated (Box 275, Folder 1)
      Contains two typescripts, "The Mystical Element in Judaism: The Exaltation of Man" by Heschel and an "Introduction Between God and Man" by F.A. Rothschild.
    - Man, 1960-1964 (Box 275, Folder 2)
      Corrected typescript drafts, fragments, photocopied typescripts, and some correspondence on a variety of topics including ambition, human rights, Soviet Jewry, human nature, man as a symbol of God, and Judaism. Also includes article written by Heschel in The Torch, "Should the United Synagogue of America Join The World Zionist Organization? No says: Abraham Joshua Heschel."
    - [Publications], 1962, 1966, 1976 (Box 275, Folder 3)
      A mix of publications and clippings. Includes a copy of a Yiddish poem on auto-da-fé, "The Pathos of Liberal Theology" by Van A. Harvey reprinted from the Journal of Religion, and an essay, הערות, by Heschel removed from an unknown publication.
    - German Articles, 1963 (Box 275, Folder 4)
      Photocopy of authors contract for "Das Gebet als Äusserung und Einfühlung" of the Monatschrift, Volume 83.
    - קוסוב, 1964 (Box 275, Folder 5)
      Transliteration: Ḳosov
      Translation: [Rabbi Nachman from] Kosov
      Contains a letter about Rabbi Nachman from Kosov, a copy of Heschel's article about him, and a mixture of typescripts and handwritten notes (presumably in preparation of the article).
    - [שונות, לא חשוב?]: Theology, circa 1964 (Box 275, Folder 6)
      Transliteration: Shonot, lo ḥashuv
      Translation: Miscellaneous, Not Important?
      Primarily handwritten notes, but also includes clippings and typescript fragments related to a variety of theological and philosophical themes including value, absurdity, faith, and image of self. Also includes typescript "Quest for Exaltation: Blessing or Curse?" written by Heschel.
    - [Miscellaneous writings], circa 1964 (Box 275, Folder 7)
      Primarily handwritten notes related to a variety of topics including Judaism, Israel, and reverence. Also includes a letter with two draft copies of "The Dilemma of the Space Age" which was prepared from a recorded interview with Heschel in 1963.
    - Quotations from Heschel made by others and references to him, 1964, 1970-1971 (Box 275, Folder 8)
      Mix of clippings, articles, and editorials either quoting Heschel or written by Heschel.
    - [Miscellaneous writings], 1964, 1992-1993 and undated (Box 275, Folder 9)
      Primarily typescripts of articles and addresses by Heschel. Includes Heschel's address at the New York Conference on Soviet Jewry; "What Happens" (Heschel makes reference to Civil Rights and the Jews of Soviet Russia); "The Study of Torah"; "Soul Threatening Situations: from the Kiln of Jewish Existence" translated by Aryeh Cohen; "Chosen People: not a title but a yoke" (in Ma'ariv) translated by Samuel Dresner; "One the Day of Hate", a poem translated by Leonard Wolf; and typed notes on talk of Rabbi J.B. Soloveitchik. Also includes a letter related to the establishment of the Abraham Joshua Heschel Center for Nature Studies.
    - Bibliography, circa 1966 (Box 276, Folder 1)
      A mix of typescripts, publications, handwritten notes and clippings. Includes a number of Heschel essays including "Some Basic Issues of Jewish Religious Education," "The Relevance of Prophecy," and "A Generation that Knows the Testimony but is Powerless to Testify."
    - [No Religion is an Island], 1966 (Box 276, Folder 2)
      Primarily annotated and corrected typescripts presumably related to Heschel's article "No Religion is an Island." Also includes a handwritten outline for the article.
    - גנזי הישע, 1967, 1968 (Box 276, Folder 3)
      Transliteration: Ginze Ha-Yesha
      Typescript of Heschel's Ginze HaYesha, with published version in ha-Doʼar (August 1967); Heschel's editor's note in Panim al Panim (12 May 1967).
    - Israel Essay, 1967, 1971 (Box 276, Folder 4)
      Consists of two short essays on the 1967 Six-Day War and an original manuscript "Why Israel is Important to Jewish People."
    - VII, 1968 (Box 276, Folder 5)
      Contains a corrected manuscript "Eldad and Medad - A Rabbinic Portrait," written by Heschel, with a cover letter from the editor at Harvard Theological Review returning the manuscript.
    - [Parables], 1969-1971; 1 of 2 (Box 276, Folder 6)
      Primarily typed parables on variety of topics including The Baal Shem Tov, Hasidism, and Mishnah. Also contains two letters from Heschel to Lily and royalty reports for Man's Quest for God.
    - [Parables], 1969-1971; 2 of 2 (Box 276, Folder 7)
    - Education: Education St. Louis, circa 1960s (Box 276, Folder 8)
      Primarily incomplete and annotated typescripts of several articles written by Heschel including "What is religious about religious education?", "Needs and Ends", and "Idols in the Temple."
    - [Idols in the Temple], circa 1960s (Box 276, Folder 9)
      Lightly corrected typescript of Heschel's article "Idols in the Temple."
    - Heschel retype, circa 1960s; 1 of 2 (Box 276, Folder 10)
      Annotated typescripts and photocopied typescripts regarding Israel.
    - Heschel retype, circa 1960s; 2 of 2 (Box 276, Folder 11)
    - קאצק, circa 1960s (Box 277, Folder 1)
      Transliteration: Ḳotsḳ
      Includes typescript of "HaYehudi Shel Mizrach Europa" by Heschel, lecture by Monsignor Myles M. Bourke, photocopy of back page of 1965 edition of Man's Quest for God, and photocopy of newspaper article "Mapeka B'olam Ha'chassidut" by Heschel.
    - [Miscellaneous manuscripts], circa 1960s (Box 277, Folder 2)
      Various manuscripts by and about Abraham Joshua Heschel, including Heschel's article "The Concept of Man in Jewish Thought." Also includes an incomplete manuscript with chapters about Heschel by Maurice Friedman and "Cry Out to Ninevah! Abraham Joshua Heschel on Militarism, Nuclear War, and Conscience", edited by Burt Jacobson.
    - New Island, circa 1906s; 1 of 3 (Box 277, Folder 3)
      Primarily corrected typescript with some handwritten notes, presumably a draft of Heschel's 1966 article "No Religion is an Island."
    - New Island, circa 1906s; 2 of 3 (Box 277, Folder 4)
    - New Island, circa 1906s; 3 of 3 (Box 277, Folder 5)
    - [Papers], circa 1960s (Box 277, Folder 6)
      Contains two typed papers written by Heschel: "Paper on Youth" (draft) and "The Patient as a Person."
    - Race, circa 1960s (Box 277, Folder 7)
      Primarily typescripts that appear to be drafts of essays related to religion, Israel, and neutrality.
    - Bonds, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 277, Folder 8)
      Annotated typescripts regarding the Kotzker and Kierkegaard.
    - Kierkegaard [Abraham J. Heschel, Hasidism and Kierkegaard], circa 1960s-1970s (Box 277, Folder 9)
      Photocopied typescript regarding Kierkegaard and Hasidism.
    - Israel essay, 1970 (Box 278, Folder 1)
      Correspondence related to the publication of an article written by Heschel titled "Why Israel is Important to Jewish People."
    - Kalevala, circa 1970 (Box 278, Folder 2)
      Photocopied typescript primarily regarding the state of Israel, but also touches on the Jews of Russia. Presumably written by Heschel.
    - Study, circa 1970 (Box 278, Folder 3)
      Mix of annotated typescripts and handwritten notes. Includes excerpts of publications by other writers and an event program for The College of Jewish Studies' "Private Dinner of Community Leaders."
    - [Zionism], circa 1970 (Box 278, Folder 4)
      Primarily typescripts related to Zionism.
    - [A Conversation with Rabbi Abraham J. Heschel], 1971 (Box 278, Folder 5)
      Typed transcript of interview with Heschel on the ABC television show Directions. Heschel was interviewed by Frank Reynolds.
    - Niebuhr, 1971 (Box 278, Folder 6)
      Mix of handwritten notes and typescripts of Heschel's eulogy for Reinhold Niebuhr.
    - [Society for the Advancement of Judaism], 1971 (Box 278, Folder 7)
      Presumably a prayer book used by the Society for the Advancement of Judaism that Heschel contributed to.
    - Ab's poetry, 1972 (Box 278, Folder 8)
      Mix of handwritten and corrected typescripts. Includes text for the gravestones of Abraham and Jacob Heschel.
    - Amnesty: To be typed, Tales, circa 1972 (Box 278, Folder 9)
      A mix of handwritten notes and annotated typescripts. Includes a number of Jewish tales and an excerpt from "A Hebrew Evaluation of Reinhold Niebuhr" written by Heschel.